Guide to the Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment Collection BCMS.0066
Brooklyn Collection
Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment Collection
1979-2001
Brooklyn Collection
BCMS.0066
6.6 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons, 2 legal size boxes, 1 document box, 4 half size document boxes and 1 flat box.
The collection contains materials concerning the activities of the Brooklyn Center for Urban Environment (BCUE), a non-profit, environmental-education program focusing on the parks and urban life in Brooklyn, New York. It was founded in 1978 by John Muir and a group of like-minded individuals that wanted to restore the Park Slope neighborhood back to its former glory. The collection is comprised of organization records, writings, lesson plans, photographs and negatives documenting the programming done by the Brooklyn Center for Urban Environment.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes newsletters, documents, photographs, negatives, and ephemera dating from 1979 to 2001. Newsletters, documents, photographs, and negatives make up a sizable portion of the collection and are especially rich in materials from the 1990s. Ephemera is a small portion of the collection but there are some significant materials that include flyers of events held by the center.
Historical Note
The Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment (BCUE) was first founded in 1978 as the Prospect Park Environmental Center or PPEC. Its founder John Muir started the organization with a few volunteers as a response to a growing urban crisis. He served as executive director and president until December of 2001. Its original intent was to teach environmental stewardship and protection in Prospect Park and its nearby neighborhoods; the center expanded to serve every neighborhood in Brooklyn and parts of New York City. The staff of BCUE led many school programs, workshops for teachers, and walking tours for adults.
The organization called several places its home; from its initial headquarters at the Picnic House and later move to the Tennis House on Prospect Park West, to Floyd Bennett Field and finally Gowanus. The organization dropped "Brooklyn" from its name some time in 2008 and became the Center for the Urban Environment (CUE) as it provided programing and workshops throughout New York City. The nonprofit organization abruptly announced it was closing its doors on April 6, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
Due to sensitive personal information, certain materials in box 11 are restricted. Other materials open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Amy Peck, 2019.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series: Series 1: Newsletters "City Green" are arranged in chronological order. Series 2: Educational Planning is arranged by school number or community school district number and program or original folder name. Series 3: Attended Workshops are arranged chronologically. Series 4: Empire State Partnership Project/PS 139 is organized in chronological order. Series 5: Photographs and Negatives are arranged alphabetically by name of program or place.
Related Materials
Brooklyn newsletter collection (ARC.174)
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The majority of the materials in this collection are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact cbhreference@bklynlibrary.org at least two weeks prior to research visit.
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Prospect Park (New York, N.Y.); Natural environment; Community centers -- New York (State) -- Kings County
- Series 1: Newsletters
  - City Green, 1979-1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - City Green, 1990-1999 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - City Green (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Environmental Education Advisory Council, 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series 2: Educational Planning
  - Arches and Bridges Program at PS 321, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Programming for Community School District 16, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Documents for Community School District 20, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - NYSCA - Application CSD 20, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - PS 99 - Asimov School for Science, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Research on Albemarle and Kenmore Terraces (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Project Resources - Brooklyn Bridge and Old Stone House, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Decorative Art Examples (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Storyboards (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Carrie Isoldi Documents, 1997, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Invoices, 1994, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Notes, 1989, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Community School District 13, 1997-1998 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - School Program Delivery Plan for CSD 13, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Community School District 18, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - School Program Delivery Plan CSD 19, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Community School Districts 24, 25, 28, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Community School District 32, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Flyers - Public Programs, 1979-2003 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Bibliography, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Reference Resources, circa 1998 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Hiring Documentation & Notes, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Program Mockups, 1990-1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Instructional Manuals & Teacher Packets, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Dan Wiley Notes, 1994-1995 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Feedback Notes, 1982, 1992, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Teaching Resources, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - CSD/BCUE Proposal, 1998-1999 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Arts in Education, A+B, SPIN (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Photographer Contacts and Miscellaneous Photographs, circa 1995 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Flyers (Folder Flat File)
  - Oversize Pamphlets (Folder Flat File)
  - Goal (Folder Flat File)
- Series 3: Attended Workshops
  - Teacher's Manual - American Landscape Painting, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    American Landscape; Teaching
  - Workshops at Cooper-Hewitt Museum: Introduction, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Paper and Forms, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Session 1: Using Architecture in the Classroom Workshop, 1992 February 8 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Session 2: Architecture of the Neighborhood, 1992 February 28 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Session 3: Mapping Neighborhood History (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Series 4: Empire State Partnership Project/PS 139
  Conditions Governing Access
  Due to sensitive personal information, certain materials in box 11 are restricted. Other materials open to researchers without restriction.
  - Proposal and Budget, 1997-1999 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Proposal Notes, 1997-1999 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - ESP Summer Seminar, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - ESP Summer Seminar, 1998 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - New York State Council Arts/ ESP Project, 1999-2000 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - NYC Partnership for Arts and Education (NYCPAE) - PS 139, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - ESP Website and Web Seminar, 199 October 15 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Lesson Plan: Decorative Art, 1992 July 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - ESP/ PS 139 Attendance sheets, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - ESP Planning Meeting and Notes, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - ESP Spring Meeting, 1998 May 5 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Empire State Partnership Project/PS 139 Culminating Event, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - ESP Summer Seminar, 1999 July 25 - July 30 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - ESP Funders, 1999 July 25 - July 30 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - ESP Goals and Objectives, 1999 July 25 - July 30 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - ESP Course Description Schedule, 1999 July 25 - July 30 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - ESP Affiliation List, 1999 July 25 - July 30 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - ESP Participant Contact Information, 1999 July 25 - July 30 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - ESP Faculty Biographies, 1999 July 25 - July 30 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - ESP NYS Learning Standards, 1999 July 25 - July 30 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - ESP Peer Review through Reflective Practice, 1999 July 25 - July 30 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - ESP Statewide Peer Review, 1999 July 25 - July 30 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - ESP Resouces, 1999 July 25 - July 30 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - ESP Guest Information Sheets, 1999 July 25 - July 30 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - ESP, 1999-07-28 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - ESP/PS 139 Curricula Schedule, 2000 January - May (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - ESP/PS 139 Memos and Agenda, 2000 January - May (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - ESP/PS 139 Evaluation, 2000 April 18 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Support Literature, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Invoices, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Lesson Plans, 2000 January - May (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - BCUE Forms, 2000 January - May (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - ESP Forms Literature, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - ESP Instructors, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - ESP Calendar, 2000 September - 2001 June (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Memos/Letters, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Program Outlines, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Curriculum (K-5) (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - NYC Standards (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Program Planning (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Program Assessment (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Program Report, 1999-2001 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Surveys, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - ESP Literature, 1999-2001 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - ESP Workshops, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Consultant Contract, 1999-2000 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Consultant Contracts, RESTRICTED, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    Due to sensitive personal information, these materials are not open for research.
  - Invoices, 1999-2001 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - BCUE Literature, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- Series 5: Photographs and Negatives
  - Benjamin Banneker Academy, 1994-1995 (Box 7, Binder 1)
  - Environmental Science Summer Camp (ESSC), 1994-1998 (Box 7, Binder 1)
  - Arches and Bridges (A+B), 1995-1998 (Box 7, Binder 2)
  - Brooklyn Bridge (BB), 1992-1996 (Box 7, Binder 2)
  - Building the Bridge (BTB) (Box 7, Binder 2)
  - Farm and Village Dwellings (FVD) (Box 7, Binder 2)
  - Neighborhood Design Project/Neighborhood Design Model Project, 1994-1998 (Box 7, Binder 3)
  - Neighborhood Streetscapes (NSS), 1989-1998 (Box 7, Binder 3)
  - Neighborhood Walk, 1993-1998 (Box 8, Binder 4)
  - Row Houses (RH), 1998 (Box 8, Binder 4)
  - Shapes and Patterns in Nature (SPIN) (Box 8, Binder 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1994-1998 (Box 8, Binder 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 8, Binder 5)
  - Research, 1994-1996 (Box 8, Binder 5)
  - Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment - Ribbon cutting ceremony, 1995 May 12 (Box 9, Binder 6)
  - PS 215 School Yard Dedication - Ribbon cutting ceremony with Howard Golden, 1995 June 20 (Box 9, Binder 6)
  - BCUE/BSGS - End of School Year Ceremony (Box 9, Binder 6)
  - BCUE-Brooklyn Bridge Model (BBM) (Box 9, Binder 6)
  - BCUE/PS 163 - Class Trip/ BBM Ceremony (Box 9, Binder 6)
  - Public Tour, 1989-1990 (Box 9, Binder 6)
  - Brooklyn Gold Coast Tour, 1992 June 13 (Box 9, Binder 6)
  - Tour - Prospect Park West (Box 9, Binder 6)
  - Pratt - Engine Room (Box 9, Binder 6)
  - Underground Places (Box 9, Binder 6)
  - Brooklyn Center for the Urban Environment, circa 1996 (Box 9, Binder 6)
  - Queen of All Saints Roman Catholic Church, 1994 March (Box 9, Binder 7)
  - St. Gregory's Roman Catholic Church, 1994 (Box 9, Binder 7)
  - St. Augustine Roman Catholic Church, 1994 March (Box 9, Binder 7)
  - Our Lady of Perpetual Holy (Box 9, Binder 7)
  - Most Precious Blood Roman Church, 1994 March (Box 9, Binder 7)
  - Greenwood Baptist, 1994 April 23 (Box 9, Binder 7)
  - St. Charles Borromeo, 1994 April 23 (Box 9, Binder 7)
  - St. Barbara's Roman Catholic Church, 1994 March 5 (Box 9, Binder 7)
  - Negatives (Box 9, Binder 8)